## Taisiya Glushkova

Home page / Google Scholar / Semantic Scholar / Github / Twitter / LinkedIn glushkovato@gmail.com

I am a NLP/ML researcher with a broad interest in LLMs, Natural Language Generation Evaluation, Interpretability and Uncertainty Estimation. I recently completed my PhD at SARDINE lab at Instituto Superior Técnico, supervised by André F. T. Martins and Chrysoula Zerva. My doctoral research focused on enhancing the robustness of NLG evaluation models and developing methods that can quantify and communicate the uncertainty associated with their outputs.

## Education

PhD in Computer Science, Instituto Superior Técnico

Lisbon, Portugal

2020 - 2024

Computer Science and Engineering Department; Supervisor: André F. T. Martins Thesis title: Uncertainty Estimation and Robustness in Machine Translation Evaluation

Collaborative project MAIA (Multilingual AI Agent Assistants) in the Carnegie Mellon Portugal Program partnership involving Instituto de Telecomunicações, INESC-ID, Carnegie Mellon University and Unbabel.

Collaborative project NextGenAl (Center for Responsible AI).

MSc in Data Science, HSE University

Moscow. Russia

Computer Science Department; Supervisor: Ekaterina Artemova

2018 - 2020

BSc in Applied Mathematics and Computer Science, HSE University

Computer Science Department; Supervisor: Ekaterina Artemova

Moscow, Russia 2014 - 2018

## **Experience**

**Carnegie Mellon University** 

Pittsburgh, USA

Research Internship

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

• Robust and interpretable machine translation evaluation. Supervisor: Alon Lavie.

Instituto Superior Técnico

Lisbon, Portugal

PhD Researcher

Sep 2020 - present

• Uncertainty estimation for machine translation evaluation.

**HSE** University

Moscow, Russia

Research Internship (Part-time)

Oct 2019 - Aug 2020

• Question-answering for Russian language.

Unbabel

Lisbon, Portugal Jul 2019 - Oct 2019

Applied AI Research Summer Internship

• Language model-based data filtering and selection for machine translation.

**Digital Decisions** Data Scientist

Moscow, Russia

Feb 2019 - Mar 2020

• Hierarchical classification and routing of the customers messages.

• Named entity recognition for a speech assistant.

Diginetica

**Yandex** 

Moscow, Russia

Jun 2017 - Dec 2017

Junior Data Scientist/Engineer • Spell checker tool for search queries aimed to suggest synonymous corrections for misspelled words.

• Snippets from product reviews: extraction of ultra-concise summaries of opinions over products.

Moscow, Russia

Summer 2015

Python Software Engineering Internship

• Analysis of the personalities in the flow of search queries.

• Marking and classification of multiple object definitions, ranking them in order of relevance for users.

## **Selected Publications**

BLEU Meets COMET: Combining Lexical and Neural Metrics Towards Robust Machine Translation Evaluation Taisiya Glushkova, Chrysoula Zerva, André F. T. Martins [ACL Anthology, poster] **EAMT 2023** 

<b>Disentangling Uncertainty in Machine Translation Evaluation</b> Chrysoula Zerva, <b>Taisiya Glushkova</b> , Ricardo Rei, André F. T. Martins EMNLP 2022		[ACL Anthology, poster]
Uncertainty-Aware Machine Translation Evaluation Taisiya Glushkova, Chrysoula Zerva, Ricardo Rei, André F. T. Martins Presented at the Sixth Conference on Machine Translation (WMT21) at EMNLP 2021 EMNLP Findings 2021		[ACL Anthology, slides]
	bmission for the Metrics Shared Task rte Alves, Chrysoula Zerva, Ana C. Farinha, Coheur, André F. T. Martins	[ACL Anthology, poster]
Ricardo Rei, Marcos Treviso, Nuno M.	omission for the Quality Estimation Shared Task Guerreiro, Chrysoula Zerva, Ana C. Farinha, Christine Maroti, va, Alon Lavie, Luisa Coheur, André F. T. Martins	[ACL Anthology]
•	babel-IST 2021 Submission for the Metrics Shared Task a Zerva, Daan van Stigt, Craig Stewart, Pedro G. Ramos, ins, Alon Lavie	[ACL Anthology]
Char-RNN and Active Learning for Taisiya Glushkova, Ekaterina Artemo CICLing 2019, published in Springer Le	va	[arXiv]
Skills		
Programming languages: Tools: Main libraries: Languages:	<b>Python</b> , R, C++, HTML, CSS, LATEX Jupyter Notebook, Google Colab, git, bash numpy, pandas, matplotlib, scipy, scikit-learn, keras, pytorch, tenglish(Advanced), Russian(Native), German(A2), Portuguese	
Teaching		
Instituto Superior Técnico Teaching Assistant for Deep Learning course		Lisbon, Portugal Nov 2021 – Feb 2022
<b>HSE University</b> Teaching Assistant for NLP course Teaching Assistant for Python course		Moscow, Russia Sep 2018 – Dec 2019 Sep 2016 – Sep 2018
University Projects		
Graduation Thesis (MSc), DaNetQA: a dataset for binary question answering in Russian		2019 – 2020
Coursework, Detecting Uncertain Information in Natural Language Texts		2018 – 2019
<b>Graduation Thesis (BSc)</b> , Character Level Models for Hashtag Segmentation		2017 - 2018
Coursework, Collecting Dictionaries for Sentiment Analysis of Reviews		2016 – 2017
Coursework, Extracting Timestamps from News in English Language		2015 - 2016
Coursework, Extracting Timestamps to	from News in English Language	2015 - 2010
	managing tasks and projects in real time (analogue of Trello)	2015 – 2016 2015 – 2016
	managing tasks and projects in real time (analogue of Trello)	